<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Willy's blog (Posts about linux python containers alpine slim debian)</title><link>https://woile.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://woile.github.io/categories/linux-python-containers-alpine-slim-debian.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:santiwilly@gmail.com"&gt;Woile&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 21:52:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Moving from docker alpine to slim</title><link>https://woile.github.io/posts/moving-from-docker-alpine-to-slim/</link><dc:creator>Woile</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've been running a docker python3.x image for a long time.
I've used the base version, the slim and the alpine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially I moved from the base python3.6 to the python3.6-slim and everything
went great. The main win was that no change was required in the Dockerfile,
it was smaller and more secure (less dependencies, more security, right?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a while, I decided to move from slim to alpine, because of the size benefit.
While doing the migration I found these drawbacks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Renaming dependencies&lt;/strong&gt;. I had to convert from &lt;code&gt;apt&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;apk&lt;/code&gt; for every dependency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Working with edge&lt;/strong&gt;. There's always a problem with the edge repository.
Sometimes it's down. Sometimes the packages are broken.
You have to dig a lot in order to have a proper configuration.
Like using &lt;code&gt;--no-cache&lt;/code&gt; flag in apk. Or setting up the edge repo, then having to upgrade &lt;code&gt;apk-tools&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This kind of problems break our pipeline when there's no new commit. And I don't want this.
That's why I've decided to move back to &lt;code&gt;slim&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't get me wrong, alpine is great, small and secure, and if you don't have many edge dependencies,
I guess it'll work flawlessly, and I would totally use it.
But our image unfortunately has dependencies like postgis, and proj4, which fail a lot in alpine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But my story is not over with alpine, I'll try it again in the future.
I know with time it will get better and better, and I'll understand it more and more.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>linux python containers alpine slim debian</category><guid>https://woile.github.io/posts/moving-from-docker-alpine-to-slim/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2019 15:34:43 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>